Okay now what do we do what is next
exactly getting there right so we have now
told you how to evaluate a policy.
.
Now the trick comes in or how to how to improve
the policy how to solve the MDP basically
I mean so this is called evaluation so this
is called control sometimes right how do I
learn to control the MDP so this is kind of
terminology inherited from I mean so legacy
terminology so this is inherited from control
theory so now I want to know control so I
have evaluation and I have control right so
I have evaluation i have done that.
So how do I how do I do control very simple
right so I evaluate pixel policy by evaluate
I do generalize policy iteration so not the
extreme form with that I just basically the
answer is positive fraction so I fix the policy
? evaluated using this kinds of trajectories
I do not run it until convergence right so
I just evaluated on few trajectories right
what do I mean the evaluation on a few trajectories
here I start from SIM status.
Just keep running the trajectory multiple
times and then take the average and you say
the C value for status right I have no guarantees
that this value that I have computed is a
true value for status under the policy ? look
in some approximation of that but I am happy
I will stop there right oh yeah this is one
thing about generalized policy trajectory
I did mention right so you do not have to
value we do not have to find the true value
of a state also.
As long as you can find an approximate value
for the state right you can keep going and
do here then release policy information that
is essentially what we will do here so we
take a state we take some samples from the
states right and then find the value and then
you can go and try to be greedy with respect
to that value function okay so any problems
that you see here how will you be greedy with
respect to value function
that way what is the problem being greedy
that way I need that ? need the expected RSA.
I just told you we doing Monte carol methods
because we do not have any of those or we
do not need any of those and I can work with
a sample model right but now you are telling
you just use that expression to be greedy
I cannot how do I get it on that you already
know how to do it good throw a chocolate you
of all people know the answer do not use the
v function use the Q function is the Q value
function.
I do remember I told you that and you want
to recover a policy from the queue all you
need to be you just look at the values of
those actions at the state I do not need to
look ahead, right so when I do control I use
the Q function, now things get really interesting
so how will they just do Monte Carlo evaluation
for the Q function, exactly so basically starts
with an s fix in A right and then follow ? thereafter.
Then some of the rewards the summation and
that gives me one sample for sa right let
us straight forward enough I then I do this
again I had another than other physically
no physically no physically in it so the crucial
thing is I start from a sign it take a okay,
suppose I reach S again what do I do okay
forget it let us not even go there okay there
is even more fundamental question than that
okay.
So I did S I did A I get s one here okay I
did some A one that is how action that suggested
by policy ? right so this is equal to right
so ? of s1 is a one so I do a one right now
can I consider this as a sample taken from
s1A1 you would think so it turns out that
if you do this you get into all kinds of problems
mainly because you draw a disproportionately
larger number of samples from actions corresponding
to ?.
As opposed to actions that are not corresponding
to ?, so it tends to terms of it sets up some
conditions in which converges cannot be guaranteed
right so you will get somewhere answers so
you only have to know I want to evaluate all
sa paths right only then I can do a policy
improvement right there only evaluate the
actions corresponding to ? then I cannot do
policy improvement right so turns out that
I will be disproportionately evaluating actions
corresponding to ? right and therefore we
never do this right.
This whole sample and I use it only for updating
the value of q SI at all the sample value
is only for q SI and never use it for qs any
one so if I want update the value of Q s 1
a 1 I need to start from s 1 a 2 a 1 and then
follow up I that after another thing you are
drawing disproportionately large number of
samples about one thing right it turns out
it sets up some kind of instability in the
convergence it is a little tricky.
And in fact for a long time the convergence
was of open question for updating on s1e1
also right in fact If we look at look at the
older version of the textbook they actually
say in the textbook it is still open question
because the text book was written in 97 and
it was proven only in 2002 that it will not
converge if you do that and they had to actually
work on for two decades to get to the answer
is a little tricky to give you the intuition.
But the intuition is that so you are getting
too many samples of one thing therefore the
rate of convergence for this that SA is much
faster than s1a1 will be much faster than
the other kinds of things and therefore that
you get up to get all kinds of problems, so
11 probably convergent phase 2 only to use
the first state for state in first action
even longer than what yeah I mean I can estimate
the value.
But what will they do with it right I mean
I can assume it only ? right I cannot do policy
improvement on that having said all of this
it is only for convergence issues right it
turns out most cases in practice if you update
for s1e1 also it works okay in practice it
works but you cannot guarantee convenience
so guaranteeing convergence you should do
it only on the initial state.
So now once I say that you have to do it only
on the initial state you exploring starts
becomes even more important and because you
have to start at every state every action
you have to do that often right so that you
can get a good estimate for it and so you
cannot be greedy at a particular state if
unless you have taken at least a good fraction
of the actions from the state right and try
to estimate the thing so those becomes important.
So one way of avoiding exploring starts right
again it is not clear whether this kind of
approaches
is going to be convergent is to use something
called a epsilon soft policy right, so whenever
I say do a policy improvement I do not give
you the greedy policy I give you a policy
that is mostly greedy right so most of the
probability will go to one action and some
of the probability will get distributed to
all the other actions okay.
So when I start from anywhere and earn a trajectory
there is a probability of me sampling all
the actions from all the states is not just
the ? action corresponding to ? but I can
sample all the actions from all the states
so these are called epsilon soft policies,
right so epsilon soft it means that every
action has at least a probability of epsilon
being taken from every state right so uniformly
random policy is an epsilon soft policy right.
An epsilon greedy execution of a policy is
also epsilon soft policy and where the epsilon
is a epsilon by n soft policy epsilon greedy
policy is an epsilon by n soft policy right
a purely random policy would be some for some
epsilon it is a 1/n soft policy rate if I
have n actions it is 1 by n soft policy state
action tap they did can you see how much yes
says this is a very simple straightforward
thing right.
It depends on the number of samples you draw
right so there are rates of convergence that
you can establish based on the number of samples
inequality if you knew the transition probabilities
and other things you could apply concentration
inequalities there yeah good I do not recall
the actual results but you could apply concentration
abilities yeah sadly same innocence more like
a textbook exercise application of concentration
inequalities.
But little complicated because the distribution
you are sampling from is this horrendous the
distribution that rolls in your oh in this
case it is me fine right it is just a Markov
chain I fixed a ? right I have fixed up I
so there is no question of picking in actions
here right so it just becomes a Markov chain
and essentially I can drink this valley computational
approach and it is very easy to show keen
convergence and rates of convergence all of
the things you can go here it become tricky.
Because they keep changing the policy from
one step to the other so it becomes a little
tricky to show convenient right so epsilon
soft policy so now the question becomes that
we showed you policy iteration converges right
but that is assuming that you are greedy with
respect to the previous policies value function
now I am saying do not be greedy be epsilon
soft with respect to the previous value.
And will this converge and if so to what okay
and we are running out of time so it will
converge and it converges to an optimal epsilon
soft policy where the more highest probability
will be given to the optimal action provider
do you have a very specific way of generating
the epsilon soft policy from the previous
iteration right so it is essentially you take
the greedy policy okay make it epsilon greedy
or whatever epsilon by n greedy or something
n epsilon greedy.
And then keep doing this so you will converge
to something that is optimal in the sense
the highest probability will be on the optimal
action okay there is a very simple proof given
in the textbook I encourage you to look at
it just so you know and themes any questions
from this, there is one other topic that I
have to cover under Monte Carlo methods which
is do with something called important sampling.
This goes back to one of the questions raised
earlier about doing epsilon greedy exploration
and so on so forth so if I am using an epsilon
soft policy right whenever for non exploring
starts right I am not really getting what
I want right I am actually solving for something
else right and if you want to evaluate a deterministic
policy right we saw that you needed through
exploring starts right if you want to evaluate
a deterministic policy certainly have to do
exploring stats.
And I cannot do my usual exploration of the
entire state space and then estimate the value
of the policy ? so why because this will no
longer be the policy ? right so ideally what
I want is a situation where I can behave however
I want in the state space but should give
you the value for any policy that you ask
me is it possible can a d couple the policy
that I am evaluating from the policy that
I am using for behaving right.
So such kinds of methods are called
of policy methods so whatever you have talked
about so far are called on policy methods
why because the samples were generated by
the policy which I am trying to evaluate whether
it is here or here right in both cases when
the samples are being generated it is with
respect to the policy that I am trying to
evaluate right in our policy methods the sample
will be generated by a different policy.
But I will try to evaluate a different policy
technique we have 10 more minutes
okay let me let me try and do the simple thing
right so essentially so I what I am looking
at this I am I want to compute the expectation
of some function f ( X) where X is sample
from some distribution P this is the rotation
for this sum of f of X is there and X is some
random variable right and X is sample from
some distribution P.
So this is the expectation that I want to
compute let us keep it simple so that is assume
it is a discrete distribution so essentially
a sum over X right
so this is the expectation now suppose I do
not have access to p okay but I have some
way of sampling X this is exactly one of the
distribution we have whatever we have the
setup that we are here right so then what
will I do so I use P and asked me to give
you ask you to give me an X.
And you will say three then you will say for
you will say three 4839 let us keep telling
me numbers like this now what I will do is
I will plug in 3 for 8 9 whatever I plug that
into f of X I will add up all the values of
f of x divided by n it will give you a number
right so I how I approximate this is essentially
very checks I was sampled from people this
is how i do this right.
But now let us say that I know what I know
something about the probability of certain
outcomes okay but you can only tell me things
according to Q let us say so you are going
to give me numbers according to Q so Q is
a different coin that you are tossing right
so instead of selling me 338 or something
that now we are going to tell me 88 97 3874
or something that I
so three and four occurred a lot of times
in the first sequence of numbers I gave you.
But three or four occur very few times now
but eight and nine occur more right so now
what I do is I am saying that I do not have
p but I have some other distribution how do
I do this so I have some other function Q
alright so I am going to do this
is it finds people are okay with that so I
am going to rewrite this as right, so I have
taken the expectation off of X with respect
to P and I written it as the expectation of
some quantity with respect to the distribution
q.
So what is this quantity it is f of X but
waited by the ratio of the probabilities right
if are equated with ratio of the probability
now I want to approximate this so what will
I do I will do this
so for every sample you give me I will compute
f of X right and also the x this ratio of
P by Q and then we will add up everything
and take the average that will give me the
average of f of X if the samples are drawn
according to p right.
So I said fine so everybody is with me write
this equivalence you are all agreeing so this
quantity is called the
importance factor it tells you how important
is the specific X in determining the expectation
of f of X with respect to P when I am drawing
samples according to Q so it gives me the
relative difference in their probability so
if P is very large and Q is very small then
the importance will be very large for that
X.
So if P of X is very small and pure fix is
very large then the importance will be small
I do not care right because I am only interested
in P of X if there are comparable probabilities
then I will just use it as it is right P of
XY q of x will be 1 I will be using as it
is so it is fine right so if Q if X happens
to be more frequent under Q then I want to
give it a lower weight when they compute the
expectation of X happens to be less frequent
under Q then under p I want to give it more
weight when I am computing the expectation
so this way it is called importance waiting.
And importance weight I am sorry important
factor or importance weight right and this
whole way of sampling to determine the expectations
is called any guesses important sampling
yeah I am assuming p and q are no it is just
that you are not able to sample from P notable
to draw samples from p to draw samples from
q can you think of a situation where that
might happen when you want to draw a samples
from a distribution I told you that I have
to find thee this CD F.
So for serious one or the CDF is hard to compute
right4p so the Q CDF might be easier to compute
earth might be easier to actually simulate
samples from Q then from p right so in such
cases I might want to do this important sample
right or in the cases where we are talking
about I will have a deterministic policy or
I have a policy that is hard for me to execute
I have some random behavior policy right.
So I use the random behavior policy and generate
trajectories some my f of X will become my
gt-right the random sample I draw for the
return I take from the trajectory right and
my P and Q will be policies according to which
I am behaving but so is there any condition
that we have to be careful about here QX will
become zero right away if Q X becomes 0 then
it is going to become undefined.
So one DC wait assume is that the Q X is not
0 for any X but that is too strong a condition
what we need to assume is QX is nonzero for
any X for which px is non zero so 40 x 0 again
kind of fed gen say that okay does not matter
but if px is nonzero then Q X has to be non
0 and 1 DC way to ensure that QX is nonzero
for any PX is epsilon soft okay yeah so whatever
yes of soft matte is another way of generating
in epsilon policy here right.
So however you generate it which could be
epsilon DD epsilon of whatever the saying
they should ensure that every action has atleast
some small epsilon probability of being picked
so that way for whatever be the policy that
you want to estimate the value for this will
never become zero whenever you want right
so that is a good thing so this is all fine
right so one small aside it turns out that
this can suffer from instabilities if you
are trying to do this numerically we are trying
to do this why is that.
Because for cases where px is non zero but
QX is close to zero the importance weights
can become very large it rare events under
QX right which are not right under PX the
importance can become very large disproportionately
large and so you can cause severe oscillations
in your estimations that if you add 1 1 1sample
like this so what people typically do is instead
of doing this right instead of dividing by
1 by n.
They do
so the ratio PA x qi becomes very large it
will happen in the numerator and in the denominator
so it kind of the ratio will be kept reasonable
it would not oscillator too much okay so this
is called the normalized important sampling
this is please do not read anything in this
place okay, so this is also an estimate of
this but this turns out to have slightly higher
bias than that when that will have a higher
variance.
So for every sample that you draw it can fluctuate
tremendously right there which will not fluctuate
as much for every sample and in the limit
both converge to the same answer so we are
all happy right but so this is weight over
this normalized important sampling is considered
better in practice because it is a lot more
stable okay, so this let us it with the Polish
sampling so I am going to stop today.
So keep the important sampling in your mind
somewhere right when you come to class on
Wednesday I will tell you how to use important
sampling to do of policy learn okay we will
work out exactly what is that p and what is
the cube that we have to use for important
sampling okay that will take me about 15 minutes
and after that we will move to chapter 6 that
will be the end of chapter five so we are
done most of certified today so there will
be small bit of chapter five left in the next
class and after that we will move chapter
six.